Guide to the Ephraim Douglass Adams Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ephraim Douglass Adams papers
1730-1931
SC0142
Adams, Ephraim Douglass, 1865-1930.
7.25 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of James D. Adams, 1975, 1981.
Information about Access
None.
Biographical Note
Ephraim Douglass Adams was born in Decorah, Iowa, on December 18, 1865. Adams attended Grinnell College and graduated from the University of Michigan in 1887, receiving a doctorate in 1890. He became principal of the high school in McGregor, Iowa, in 1887-88, and after his graduate work he served in Washington on the staff of the Eleventh Census, 1890-91. He then joined the history department of the University of Kansas, and eventually became professor of European History, resigning to accept an appointment at Stanford in 1902.
Professor Adams taught European history for his first six years at Stanford, but in 1908, with the reorganization of the department, he took over recent American history, and especially British-American relations. Adams also became head of the department in 1908 and served in that capacity until 1922.
Adams' published works include The Control of the Purse in the United States Government (1894), The Influence of Grenville on Pitt's Foreign Policy (1904), British Interests and Activities in Texas (1910), The Power of Ideals in American History (1913), Great Britain and the American Civil War (1925).
Adams was collaborating with Charles Francis Adams, Jr. on the Life of Charles Adams, Sr., at the time of Charles Francis Adams, Jr.'s death in 1915. When E.D. Adams used some of the research materials gathered for this biography in his work Great Britain and the American Civil War it led to a major controversy (here called the Ford Controvery) with Worthington C. Ford, President of the Massachusetts Historical Society.
When Herbert Hoover assumed the direction of the wide-reaching operation of Belgian relief, Adams called to his attention the importance of preserving all the significant records of his administration. From this correspondence arose the project a War Library. Professor Adams directed the acquisition of materials throughout Europe after the war; these papers formed the original collections in the new Hoover War Library (later renamed the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace).
Adams died of pneumonia on September 1, 1930.
Scope and Content Note
The E.D. Adams Papers, dating from 1730 to 1931 (1900-1931 bulk), include correspondence, manuscripts and typescripts of some of Adams' writings, research materials, and a small amount of Stanford administrative records. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, but the letters for the years 1929 and 1930 are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
The Adams papers contain a substantial amount of correspondence concerning the Stanford History Department and the Hoover War Library. Adams' correspondence with Hoover touches on other university matters also, such as the tenure system and the Stanford Union.
The Adams papers also include correspondence pertaining to the establishment of the National Archives (J. Franklin Jameson).
E.D. Adams was collaborating with Charles Francis Adams, Jr., on The Life of Charles Francis Adams, Sr. at the time of C.F. Adams, Jr. 's death in 1915. When E.D. Adams used some of the research materials gathered for this biography in his work Great Britain and the American Civil War it led to a major controversy (here called the Ford Controversy) with Worthington C. Ford, President of the Massachusetts Historical Society. E.D. Adam's documentation of this dispute has been separated into its own series, the Ford Controversy.
Major correspondents include the following:
Charles Francis Adams, Jr.
Nina Almond
American Historical Association
Max Farrand
Worthington C. Ford
Herbert C. Hoover
Lou Henry Hoover
J. Franklin Jameson
H. Barrett Learned
Sir charles Lucas
Ralph Lutz
Edgar E. Robinson
Lady Agatha Russell
Ray Lyman Wilbur
Frederick Jackson Turner
Outline of Arrangement
Correspondence Boxes 1 - 2
Publications Boxes 3 - 7
Ford Controversy Boxes7 - 8
Miscellaneous Box 8
Administrative Records Box 9
Access Terms
Adams, Charles Francis, 1835-1915; Adams, Elisabeth Douglass.; Adams, Ephraim Douglass, 1865-1930.; Adams, Ephraim, 1818-1907.; Almond, Nina.; American Historical Association; Farrand, Max, 1869-1945.; Fester, Ruth.; Ford, Worthington C.; Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.; Jameson, J. Franklin, (John Franklin), 1859-1937.; Learned, H. Barrett.; Lucas, Charles Prestwood,, Sir,, 1853-1931.; Lutz, Ralph Haswell, 1886-1968.; Massachusetts Historical Society..; National Archives (U.S.).; Ritchey, Lawrence.; Robinson, Edgar E.; Russell, Agatha,, Lady.; Stanford University. Department of History. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Stanford University. Stanford Union.; Treat, Payson J. (Payson Jackson), 1879-1972; Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; College teachers--Tenure--California--Stanford.; Manuscripts (for publication).; Notes.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1900-1930
  - 1900-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jan-Oct 1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nov-Dec 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jan-Sep 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oct-Dec 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jan-Jun 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jul-Dec 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - A-H, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - J-P, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - R-W, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - A-B, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - C-G, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - H, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - H-J, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - M-R, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - S-W, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Publications
  - Our United States of America
    - Outline of story, manuscript and typescript (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 1, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 2, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 3, typescript (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 4, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 5, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 6, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 7, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 8, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 9, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 10, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 11, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 12, ms. and typescript (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 13, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 14, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 15, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 16, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 17, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 18, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 19, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 20, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 21, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 22, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 23, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 24, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 25, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 26, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 27, ms. and typescript (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 28, ms. and typescript (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 29, ms. and typescript (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 30, ms. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 31, ms. and typescript (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Teacher's Manual (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Teacher's Manual (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Teacher's Manual (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Notes, manual of illustrations (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Notes, manual of illustrations (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Great Britain and the American Civil War
    - Vol. I, galley (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Vol. II, galley (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Notes (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Illustrations (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Reviews (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Part I, typescript [bound] (Box 6)
    - Part II, typescript [bound] (Box 6)
    - Part III, typescript [bound] (Box 6)
  - Life of Charles Francis Adams
    - Vol. I, editing notes (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Vol. II, chapters 1, 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Vol. II, chapters 7, 16, 17 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Vol. II, chapters 18, 19 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Vol. II, chapter 20 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Vol. II, chapter 21 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Vol. II, chapter 22 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Vol. II, chapter 23, 24 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with Charles Francis Adams, Jan-Mar 1914 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Charles Francis Adams, Apr-Jun 1914 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with Charles Francis Adams, Jul-Dec 1914 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Why We Are at War With Germany, circa 1917 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Ford Controversy
  - Correspondence with Learned and Jameson, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Material sent to Learned and Jameson from Adams (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence re the question of collaboration and pledge to Charles Francis Adams, circa 1913-1915 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Analysis of correspondence with Charles Francis Adams and Worthington C. Ford on The Life of Charles Francis Adams (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Research materials used for The Life of Charles Francis Adams held by E.D. Adams (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Lange's Biographical Notes used by Adams for The Life of Charles Francis Adams (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Bibliography of Adams' writings (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - A Collection of Letters of Ephraim and Elisabeth Douglass Adams. Section 3. Edited by James Douglass Adams. Iowa Historical Society, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - A Collection of Letters of Ephraim and Elisabeth Douglass Adams. Section 4. Edited by James Douglass Adams. Iowa Historical Society, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Hoover, Herbert. Recollections of Herbert Hoover by E.D. Adams (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Hoover, Herbert. Clippings (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Lewis, Mrs. John. Diary, [Adams' typescript transcription], 1730-1775 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Lecture on the Monroe Doctrine (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Patrick, M.R. Diary, 15 Oct. 1846 - 26 March 1848 [Adams' typescript transciption] (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Patrick, M.R. Diary, Jan-31 May 1862 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Patrick, M.R. Diary, Jun-15 Sep 1862 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Patrick, M.R. Diary, 15 Sep-25 Dec 1862 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Patrick, M.R. Diary, 26 Dec 1862-5 May 1863 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - A Personal Reaction to the Great War, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Notes, miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Notes, miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Reviews: - Autobiography of Charles Francis Adams, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Reviews - Rivalry of the United States and Great Britain over Latin America by J.F. Rippy
  - Will, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Administrative Records
  - Faculty and Council Rules, Admissions requirements [also includes Adams' book list] (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Suggested Plan of Policy for the Reorganization and Development of Stanford University, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 2)
General note
(Taken in part from Payson Treat's A Tribute to Friend and Scholar, Stanford Illustrated Review, 10/30)